本视频由NordVPN赞助
This video is supported by NordVPN.
1969年7月16日 土星五号火箭发射升空
On the 16th of July 1969, the Saturn 5 rocket left Earth -
将阿波罗11号的宇航员送上月球
taking the Apollo 11 crew to the Moon.
这枚巨大的火箭是肯尼迪总统兑现在六十年代末登月的承诺的关键
This enormous rocket was key to achieving President Kennedy's goal
of landing a man on the Moon by the end of the decade.
但如果没有一款长相极其怪异的飞机的帮助
But without the help from an incredibly unique aircraft,
阿波罗工程的黄金时刻可能就不会准时到来
the Apollo program's golden moment might not have happened in time.
这款飞机的名字叫Guppy
The aircraft in question was called Guppy.
六十年代早期 NASA正在进行双子星计划
In the early 60's, NASA were working on the Gemini Project -
该计划包含一系列载人飞行任务 用于验证登月所需的技术
a series of crewed spaceflight missions which would demonstrate the technologies needed to go to the Moon.
随着时间的推移 NASA发现他们要应付一款非常非常大的火箭
As the decade went on, NASA found themselves working on much larger rockets.
随着庞然大物土星五号火箭的初步定型
With the designs for the massive Saturn 5 rocket taking shape,
人们意识到运输这款火箭将是一个前所未有的挑战
it was clear that transporting these giant rocket parts to the launch site was going to be an enormous challenge.
虽然土星五号是从佛罗里达州发射的
Although the Saturn 5 launched from Florida,
但它的很多组件是美国各地的外包公司制造的
many sections of the rocket were made by different companies across the United States.
每一级对于卡车或火车来说都太大了
Each stage was too large to be transported by truck or train -
所以唯一的选择就是海运
so the only option was to send them on a barge.
火箭的某些级要绕过墨西哥走巴拿马运河 全程20天
For some stages, this involved a 20 day journey around Mexico via the Panama Canal -
而登月任务时间紧 任务重 20天实数拖沓
not ideal for a program that was already under immense time pressure.
与此同时
At the same time,
波音377又叫“同温层巡航者”“Stratocruiser”
以下为方便全部翻作“377”
美国航空公司开始把自家的波音377飞机替换成现代喷气客机
US airlines were replacing their Boeing 377 Stratocruisers with more modern jet-engined airliners.
前空军飞行员John Conroy得知NASA的运输问题后
Ex-airforce pilot John Conroy was aware of NASA's transportation problems
从中看到了机遇
and saw this as an opportunity.
他从飞机报废厂买下了两架377
He bought two Stratocruisers from an aircraft broker
和他的新公司Aero Spacelines一起改装它们
and began converting them with his new company Aero Spacelines.
他们把一架377从中间切割开
They began by cutting one of the stratocruisers in half
插入一段其他377的机身 从而将机身延长5米
and inserting a section from the other stratocruiser to lengthen the vehicle by 5 meters.
然后 为了提高货舱体积
Then, to increase the size of the cargo bay,
他们在飞机上方制造了一个新的 直径六米的机身
they built a new fuselage on top of the aircraft with a massive 6 meter diameter.
虽然有了全新的机身 但Guppy只比原厂版本重量大了1.3吨
Despite the new fuselage, Guppy only weighed 1.3 tonnes more than the original plane it was made from.
然而 巨大的新机身外形导致阻力大大提升
However, the enormous new shape caused a significant amount of drag
飞机只能以360km/h的速度巡航
and the aircraft could only fly at a cruising speed of 360km/h.
NASA很怀疑这飞机能不能飞起来
NASA were very doubtful that the plane could even leave the ground -
更不用说能不能载着火箭部件横跨美国了
let alone carry their enormous rocket parts across the country.
于是 Conroy将Guppy飞到NASA在休斯敦的宇航中心进行一场飞行试验
So, Conroy flew Guppy to NASA's spaceflight center in Houston to give them a demonstration.
在展示了飞机的安全飞行能力后
After showing the plane's ability to fly safely,
NASA说真香 立即让Guppy投入使用
NASA were impressed and immediately began putting Guppy to work.
随后它就用来运送双子星计划中的火箭部件了
The aircraft began transporting components for the Gemini program,
并且把20天的运输时间缩短到了18小时
cutting a 20 day journey down to just 18 hours.
随着阿波罗工程研发工作的开始
As the Apollo program began to develop,
NASA在组装发射首枚土星五号火箭方面承受了很大的压力
NASA was under a lot of pressure to assemble and launch the first Saturn 5 rocket -
与此同时 Guppy的缺陷也开始显现
but Guppy's flaws were starting to show.
为了把货物装进飞机内
In order to load cargo into the plane,
飞机的整个后部需要卸下移开
the entire rear section of the aircraft had to be unbolted and wheeled away.
货仓是非加压的 所以某些货物因飞行中的气压变化而无法装载上去
The cargo bay wasn't pressurized, meaning certain payloads couldn't fly on the aircraft
due to the change in pressure during flight.
到了组装巨大的土星五号的时候
But when it came time to assemble the gigantic Saturn 5,
Guppy面对巨大的火箭第三级又不够大 但三级需求又很紧张
Guppy wasn't big enough to carry the massive 3rd stage, which was urgently needed for the first flight test.
NASA又找到了Conroy 让他的公司再造一个飞机
NASA went back to Conroy and asked his company to make a new aircraft.
然后就造出来了——超级Guppy
And so they made - Super Guppy.
这次 飞机是从一架军用的377改装而来 长度增加了10米
This time, the aircraft was built using a military Stratocruiser which was lengthened by an extra 10 metres.
新的货仓直径7.6米 比上一个版本宽敞多了
The new fuselage had a diameter of 7.6 meters, much wider than the previous version.
新的货仓还是全部加压的 从而允许运输更多种类的载荷
The new cargo bay was also fully pressurized, allowing more payloads to be transported.
这款更大的飞机现在终于可以运输土星五号的组件了
This larger version of the aircraft was now capable of carrying sections of the Saturn V rocket,
其中包括火箭整个第三级在内的许多重要设备单元
including the 3rd stage and the all important instrument unit.
土星五号首飞原定在1967年
The first Saturn 5 launch was scheduled for 1967 and
虽然火箭的某些分级拖延了一年之久
despite some stages being a year behind schedule,
但由超级Guppy运输的许多货物比那些船运的部件快了一年
Super Guppy delivered many of its payloads a year earlier than those traveling by barge.
1967年11月 土星五号在肯尼迪航天中心首飞
In November of 1967, the first ever Saturn 5 lifted off from the Kennedy Space Center,
不到两年后 阿波罗11号就带着人类登上了月球
less than two years before Apollo 11 would land on the Moon.
随后几年 Guppy飞行了上百万公里
Over the next few years, Guppy flew over a million kilometers -
为双子星计划和阿波罗计划运送了无数火箭部件
carrying enormous sections of delicate rocketry for the Gemini and Apollo programs.
没有Guppy NASA可能要额外花几个月运送组装土星五号火箭
Without Guppy, transporting and assembling the Saturn 5 rocket would have put NASA months -
说不定要咕上好几年
perhaps years behind schedule.
在这样一个经历过重大延误的计划中
In a program which had suffered major delays,
阿波罗11号仍能在肯尼迪总统承诺的时间期限之前5个月完成
Apollo 11 achieved Kennedy's goal with just 5 months to spare.
随后几年
Over the next couple of years,
Guppy的多种改装型被生产出来以满足NASA的需求
multiple variations of Guppy were produced to handle NASA's transportation needs.
这一机队继续在随后的国际空间站计划和天空实验室计划中为NASA提供支持
This fleet continued to support NASA during the Skylab program in the 70's and the
International Space Station program in the late 90's.
虽然是六十年代的飞机 但NASA直到今天也还在用它运输大型组件
Despite being an aircraft from the 60's, NASA still uses Guppy today to transport its largest components.
在人类最伟大的成就之一中发挥了作用后
After playing a role in one of humanity's greatest achievements,
Guppy继续激发了新的飞机型号的诞生 比如空客的大白鲸
Guppy went on to inspire a new breed of aircraft like the Airbus Beluga
能够将整个飞机机身装入货仓中
which can carry entire aircraft fuselages in its cargo bay.
虽然如今很多货机的性能已经超过了当年的Guppy
Although many cargo planes have surpassed Guppy in terms of capability,
但人们仍然不会忘记它曾是拯救阿波罗计划的功臣
it will always be remembered as the aircraft that saved the Apollo program.
它独特的设计 体现了当时工程师们为了达成目的
Its distinctive design came at a time when engineers were pushing the limits of their imaginations
不断挑战自我想象力 挖掘极限的精神
in order to achieve a seemingly impossible goal.
I recently collaborated with Astrum on a video about the largest storms in our solar system.
Be sure to check out that video and the rest of their videos for more awesome space related content.
Thanks to NordVPN for sponsoring this episode of Primal Space.
We all watch a lot of stuff online, especially when your entire country is in quarantine.
When the Apollo 11 crew returned from the Moon they were quarantined for 21 days
and missed out on a tonne of great movies and tv series.
The same thing is happening to you right now.
Streaming sites like Netflix, YouTube and Amazon Prime block certain content based on your location.
With NordVPN, you can connect to servers all over the world and unlock everything you have been missing out on.
With NordVPN, your connection is encrypted multiple times,
making all of your personal data safe and secure.
To support the channel and get 70% off, visit NordVPN.com/PrimalSpace and use the code ‘Primal Space' to sign up.
Using this exclusive link will also give you an extra month for free!
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.